Our best classical supercomputers are growing more powerful,
最高性能の古典的スーパーコンピューターは年々進化しており、
and we're becoming better at computation, including simulating systems.
システムのシミュレーションを含む計算能力も向上しています。
But simulating nature is a very difficult problem in general.
しかし、自然をシミュレートすることは、一般的に非常に難しい問題です。
My name is Victoria Lipinska and today we'll explore one of the algorithms
私はVictoria Lipinskaです。今日は、量子コンピューターで
that could make simulating nature possible on a quantum computer.
自然のシミュレーションを可能にするアルゴリズムの一つを紹介します。
Let's start with an example and consider caffeine.
例としてカフェインを取り上げてみましょう。
It's a simple molecule.
これは単純な分子です。
To represent the energy configuration of just one molecule of caffeine,
カフェイン分子一つのエネルギー配置を表現するためには、
we'd need approximately ten to the power of 48 bits.
約10の48乗ビットが必要になります。
That's ten with 48 zeros
それは1の後ろに0が48個並ぶ数で、
and its about 10% of the number of atoms in the earth.
地球上の原子の数の約10%に相当します。
And it actually gets worse.
さらに状況は悪化します。
If you have 125 orbitals and you want to store all possible
125個の軌道があり、すべての可能な
configurations, you need more memory
配置を保存しようとすると、
in your classical computer than there are atoms in the universe.
宇宙の原子の総数を超えるメモリが古典コンピューターに必要になります。
That's impossible to represent with supercomputers.
それはスーパーコンピューターでも表現できません。
There is hope for quantum computers, though,
しかし、量子コンピューターには希望があります。
because they're intrinsically good at simulating nature.
なぜなら、量子コンピューターは本質的に自然のシミュレーションが得意だからです。
For a caffeine molecule, that would mean representing
カフェイン分子の場合、それはシステムを
the system using 160 qubits.
160個のqubitで表現することを意味します。
That sounds much more manageable.
それははるかに現実的に思えます。
Various quantum algorithms have been proposed that allow
様々な量子アルゴリズムが提案されており、
smaller quantum computers to heuristically simulate nature.
小さな量子コンピューターでヒューリスティックに自然をシミュレートできます。
Enter: variational quantum eigensolver or VQE.
そこで登場するのが、変分量子固有値ソルバー（VQE）です。
VQE is an algorithm that runs partly on a quantum
VQEは量子コンピューターと
computer and partly on a classical computer.
古典コンピューターの両方で動作するアルゴリズムです。
It allows us to find values that solve a given optimization problem.
与えられた最適化問題を解く値を見つけることができます。
VQE is very closely related to other methods involving
VQEは、パラメーターの変分を用いた他の手法と
variation of parameters like the quantum approximate optimization algorithm.
非常に密接に関連しており、例えば量子近似最適化アルゴリズムなどがあります。
Identifying applications of VQE in your industry or research
あなたの業界や研究でVQEの応用を見つけることは
is something of an art, but there are loose guidelines.
一種の技術ですが、おおまかなガイドラインがあります。
Generally, VQE is applicable to problems that can be cast
一般的に、VQEは連続変数による
as an optimization problem with continuous variables.
最適化問題として定式化できる問題に適用できます。
This is the case, for example, in much of quantum chemistry.
これは、例えば量子化学の多くの分野に当てはまります。
Very often, in chemistry, we're interested in the ground state.
化学では非常に多くの場合、基底状態に関心があります。
The ground state is the state of lowest energy of the system.
基底状態とは、システムの最低エネルギー状態のことです。
In order to find the ground state energy, VQE explores
基底状態エネルギーを求めるために、VQEは
the energy for different configurations of the system
システムのさまざまな配置のエネルギーを探索し、
and looks for the lowest energy configuration.
最低エネルギーの配置を探します。
At a high level, VQE takes in a description of the quantum system
大まかに言えば、VQEは量子システムの記述を入力として受け取り、
and looks for the lowest energy.
最低エネルギーを探します。
It does this by varying the configuration of the system.
システムの配置を変化させることでこれを実現します。
To start, we have to input an appropriate description of the system
まず、システムの適切な記述を入力する必要があります。
that the quantum computer understands and a set of parameters describing it
量子コンピューターが理解できる形式と、それを記述するパラメーターのセットを
which will be optimized.
最適化します。
The quantum part of
アルゴリズムの量子部分は、
the algorithm prepares the system in a state
与えられたパラメーターのセットで記述された状態にシステムを
described by a given set of parameters and calculates the energy.
準備し、エネルギーを計算します。
While the classical part is responsible
一方、古典部分は各ステップで
for optimizing those parameters at each step.
それらのパラメーターを最適化する役割を担います。
This quantum classical process is repeated
この量子・古典的プロセスは
until we reach the lowest energy.
最低エネルギーに達するまで繰り返されます。
Let's now zoom in on what's going on under the hood.
では、内部で何が起きているかを詳しく見てみましょう。
The energy configuration is typically described in the Hamiltonian
エネルギー配置は通常ハミルトニアンで記述され、
and typically it's a really big matrix.
一般的に非常に大きな行列になります。
In algebra, to find the lowest eigenvalue of the matrix
代数的には、行列の最小固有値を求めるには、
corresponding to the lowest energy of the system,
それがシステムの最低エネルギーに対応しますが、
we would simply do singular value decomposition.
単純に特異値分解を行います。
However, the matrices we'll be looking at are exponentially large
しかし、対象となる行列は指数関数的に大きく、
and it's an exponentially difficult problem to do this algebraically.
代数的に解くことは指数関数的に困難な問題です。
This Hamiltonian has to be represented in the form
このハミルトニアンは
that the quantum computer can understand.
量子コンピューターが理解できる形式で表現する必要があります。
So translated from chemistry language to quantum computing language.
つまり、化学の言語から量子コンピューティングの言語に翻訳するのです。
No worries on the details though.
詳細は気にしなくて大丈夫です。
Ultimately there is this programable ways to translate the Hamiltonian usually
最終的には、化学でよく見られるハミルトニアンを
seen in chemistry into a Hamiltonian understandable for a quantum computer.
量子コンピューターが理解できるハミルトニアンに変換するプログラム可能な方法があります。
We then input this
次にこのハミルトニアンを
Hamiltonian together with the circuit, which we call a variational form.
変分形式と呼ばれるcircuitと一緒に入力します。
Choosing a variational form is something of an art.
変分形式の選択は一種の技術です。
Again,
繰り返しになりますが、
it represents our best guess on what the quantum state of the system could be.
それはシステムの量子状態がどうあるべきかについての最良の推測を表しています。
This variational circuit is parameterized with a set of parameters theta,
この変分circuitはパラメーターθのセットでパラメーター化されており、
and we also input an initial choice of these parameters.
これらのパラメーターの初期値も入力します。
Based on this, the quantum part of VQE:
これに基づいて、VQEの量子部分は次のことを行います。
prepares the reference state, for example, the zero state;
参照状態（例えばゼロ状態）を準備し、
uses a parameterized quantum circuit, the variational form, to prepare a quantum
パラメーター化された量子circuit（変分形式）を使って、パラメーターの初期推測値に基づく量子
state for an initial guess of parameters on the quantum computer; and it estimates
状態を量子コンピューター上で準備します。そしてハミルトニアンを通じて評価された
the energy corresponding to the state evaluated through the Hamiltonian.
状態に対応するエネルギーを推定します。
This energy estimate is then fed
このエネルギー推定値は
into the classical optimizer, which finds a new set of parameters.
古典的なオプティマイザーに渡され、新しいパラメーターのセットが求められます。
The parameters make their way back to the quantum solver again,
パラメーターは再び量子ソルバーに戻り、
and the whole process is repeated.
プロセス全体が繰り返されます。
The quantum computer finds a new energy estimate, the
量子コンピューターは新しいエネルギー推定値を求め、
classical optimizer finds a new set of parameters and so on.
古典的なオプティマイザーは新しいパラメーターのセットを求めます。これを繰り返します。
We repeat this process until the solution converges.
解が収束するまでこのプロセスを繰り返します。
That means until the difference in outcomes between steps is small enough
つまり、ステップ間の結果の差が
for our needs.
必要なレベルまで小さくなるまで続けます。
At the end, the algorithm returns that minimized energy.
最終的に、アルゴリズムはその最小エネルギーを返します。
Okay, this is great.
これは素晴らしいことです。
But you might wonder how do we know that this actually works
でも、これが実際に機能するかどうか、
and that we won't accidentally find energy lower than what we're looking for?
求めているエネルギーより低いエネルギーを誤って見つけてしまわないか気になるかもしれません。
That's a great question.
良い質問です。
It turns out that we can never estimate an energy that's lower.
実は、それより低いエネルギーを推定することは決してできません。
This is thanks to something that we call a variational principle.
これは変分原理と呼ばれるもののおかげです。
The variational principle states that the greatest lower
変分原理によれば、システムのエネルギーの
bound on the energy of the system is always its
最大の下限は常に
lowest energy corresponding to that ground state.
その基底状態に対応する最低エネルギーです。
This means that energy evaluated on any other state of that system
これはつまり、そのシステムの他の任意の状態で評価されたエネルギーは
will always be greater than the lowest energy.
常に最低エネルギーより大きくなるということです。
Therefore, with VQE we can never obtain something
したがって、VQEでは基底状態エネルギーより
lower than the ground state energy.
低い値を得ることは決してできません。
However, we can indeed converge to something
しかし、求めている最小値より
greater than the minimum we're looking for.
大きい値に収束してしまうことはあります。
This is oftentimes called a metastable solution
これは準安定解と呼ばれることが多く、
and its a challenge that researchers try to solve on a daily basis.
研究者たちが日々解決しようとしている課題です。
VQE is useful because it uses shallower circuits
VQEが有用なのは、基底状態エネルギーの推定を可能にする
compared to other protocols that allow us to estimate ground state energy.
他のプロトコルと比べて、より浅いcircuitを使用するからです。
This makes it suitable for near-term quantum hardware.
これにより、近い将来の量子ハードウェアに適しています。
In this video, we had a glimpse of what VQE can do and how it's built.
このビデオでは、VQEができることとその仕組みの一端を紹介しました。
But I encourage you to explore Qiskit in this context.
この文脈でQiskitをぜひ探索してみてください。
Even though we're still at the beginning of our quantum journey,
量子の旅はまだ始まったばかりですが、
you might already find it useful for problems you're trying to solve.
解こうとしている問題にすでに役立つかもしれません。
My name is Victoria Lipinska and this was an overview
私はVictoria Lipinskaです。今回は
of the variational quantum eigensolver algorithm.
変分量子固有値ソルバーアルゴリズムの概要をお届けしました。